What if just one
lifestyle change
could help you
avoid getting cancer,
or diabetes,
or heart disease,
or high blood pressure?
This one change could cut
your risk of chronic disease
and add years to your life.
Well, the simple solution to
so many of these problems
is to eat a healthy diet.
In other words, one centered
around whole plant foods.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I'm your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today I discuss the
safety and efficacy
of some unconventional
weight loss methods;
everything from Botox and corsets
to siphons and tapeworms.
A moderately obese person doing
moderately intense physical activity,
like biking or brisk walking, would burn
off approximately 350 calories an hour,
but most drinks, snacks,
and other processed junk
are consumed at a rate of
about 70 calories per minute.
Therefore, it only takes five minutes
for someone to wipe out
a whole hour of exercise.
Enter: the AspireAssist siphon assembly.
It's a percutaneous gastrostomy device,
meaning surgeons cut a hole
in your stomach and tunnel a fistula
out through your abdominal wall,
so after each meal you can attach
a suctioning gadget to the hole
and directly drain out
your stomach contents.
You could gorge on doughnuts,
spew them out through the hole
in your stomach, and then gorge
again on even more doughnuts.
Have your cake, and eat it too...
and three, and four times.
It's like bulimia without the aftertaste.
Seems to be the quintessential
American invention, straight
from the land that brought you
Jell-O salads, spray cheese,
and deep-fried Snickers bars.
Patients do lose weight, perhaps in
part because the fistula may interfere
with the relaxation of the
stomach wall during a meal.
The process also requires drinking
lots of water and for food
to be chewed thoroughly, both
of which may help with weight loss
in other ways by increasing hydration
and slowing eating rate.
Patients also started to make
healthier choices to avoid
unpleasant-appearing gastric
aspirate of unhealthy food choices.
The tubing is clear and
evidently fried foods look particularly
gross as they're pumped out.
All patients need to take supplemental
potassium, since it's sucked out
in the stomach juices; otherwise, they
risk becoming potassium deficient,
a common complication
in true bulimia,
but most side effects are just
minor wound complications.
Serious adverse effects like
abdominal abscesses are rare.
The big selling point is that the siphon
device does not alter the anatomy
of the gastrointestinal tract. Seems like
a low bar, but in today's Wild West
world of weight loss procedures,
you can't take anything for granted.
Case in point: the
Duodenal-Jejunal Bypass Liner.
Gastric bypass surgery works in part by
cutting out part of the small intestine
from the flow of food to help prevent
the absorption of calories.
Instead of major surgery, how about
just dropping down a couple feet
of plastic tubing to line
the intestinal walls?
The problem with the EndoBarrier
is that it has to be anchored
in the digestive tract. This is
accomplished with 10 barbed hooks
that cause lacerations, accounting
for the majority of the 891 adverse
effects reported in 1,056 patients.
That's nearly 9 out of 10.
Severe penetrating trauma,
resulting in esophageal perforation
or liver abscesses,
is thankfully more rare, occurring
in only about 1 in 27 patients.
Concern has been raised about
the palatability of the AspireAssist
stomach pump, but the most
cringeworthy endoscopic procedure
I ran across in my research
was intestinal resurfacing.
Why cover the inside of your intestines
with plastic to prevent absorption
when you can just thermally ablate
the superficial duodenal mucosa?
In other words, have your intestinal
lining burned off, or rather, resurfaced.
Surgeons have tried injecting botox into
the stomach walls of obese individuals,
hoping it would partially
paralyze their gastric muscles,
slow stomach emptying, make people
feel fuller longer, and lose weight.
It didn't work.
Researchers in Sweden tried
randomizing people to wear corsets
for 12 to 16 hours a day, seven
days a week, for nine months.
And it didn't work.
You can guess why.
The study subjects
just didn't wear them.
The corset was perceived
as uncomfortable. Duh!
Sanitized tapeworms have
evidently been widely advertised
as a weight loss remedy since
back in the early 1900s.
The fact that living tapeworms
have been discovered
during bariatric surgery operations
suggests infesting yourself
with parasites may not
be particularly effective either.
Speaking of disgusting strategies,
how about disgust itself?
A study entitled "Harnessing the power
of disgust: a randomized trial to reduce
high-calorie food appeal through
implicit priming" tried using
subliminal messages
to ruin people's appetite.
Immediately before images of healthy
foods, researchers showed people
happy images like a group of kittens
in a 20-millisecond flash.
That's too quick to
consciously register,
but the hope was to plant
a positive imprint on the brain.
Before images of high-calorie
foods like ice cream though,
they instead flashed scenes
of a cockroach on a slice of pizza,
vomit in an unclean lavatory,
a burn wound...
Apparently, it worked!
Subjects subsequently
reported a reduced desire
to eat high-calorie foods,
though this wasn't tested directly.
The researchers conclude subliminal
revulsion may be a successful tactic
to combat the onslaught of food
cues that promote unhealthy eating.
The rest of the world look on
bemused by American machinations,
penning commentaries like
"A View From Across the Pond...
Don't Let Them Eat Cake!"
A paper in the journal Obesity Surgery
entitled "What are the Yanks Doing?"
reviewed the U.S. experience with
Implantable Gastric Stimulation,
inserting electrodes into the
muscular layer of the stomach wall.
When that didn't work, we tried
Colon Electrical Stimulation.
Even more shocking
were studies like
"Repetitive electric brain stimulation
reduces food intake in humans."
Though placing deep brain
electrodes is considered a
complication-prone operation,
scientists have long pondered
whether placing an electrode somewhere
in the brain could make people eat less.
Holes were drilled through the
skulls of five obese individuals,
and wires were pushed into their brains
for electro-stimulatory exploration.
Once they poked around and found spots
where they were able to elicit convincing
hunger responses, they sent enough juice
in to fry out electro-coagulatory lesions.
It seemed to work in cats and monkeys,
but the researchers found that burning
holes in people's brains did not
produce weight loss in obese humans.
Thankfully, as I aim to explain
in my book, How Not to Diet,
healthy sustainable weight loss
isn't brain surgery.
In our next story, we look
at how sham surgery trials
have shown us that some of our most
popular surgeries are themselves shams.
Intragastric balloons arrived
with much fanfare in the 1980s,
balloons that could be
implanted into the stomach
and inflated with air or water
to fill up much of the space.
Sadly, surgical devices are often brought
to the market before there is adequate
evidence of safety and effectiveness,
and the balloons were no exception.
The Gastric Bubble had its bubble burst
when a study at the Mayo Clinic found
that 8 out of 10 balloons spontaneously
deflated, which is potentially dangerous
as they could pass into the intestines
and cause an obstruction,
but not before causing gastric
erosions in half the patients,
damaging the stomach lining.
The kicker is that in terms of inducing
weight loss, it didn't even work.
Eventually, it was pulled from the
market, but now balloons are back.
After a 33-year hiatus, the FDA started
approving a whole slew of intragastric
balloons in 2015, immediately resulting
in more than 5,000 placements.
By then the Sunshine Act had passed,
which forced drug companies
and the surgical and medical device
industry to disclose any payments
they were making to physicians
to shine a disinfecting light
on industry enticements.
By now most people know about
the overly cozy financial relationship
doctors can have with Big Pharma,
but fewer may realize that
surgeons can also get payments
from companies for
the devices they use.
The 100 top recipients of industry
payments received an unbelievable
$12 million from device
companies in a single year.
Yet outrageously, when
they published papers,
only a minority disclosed
the blatant conflict of interest.
The benefit of balloons over
most types of bariatric surgery
is that they're reversible, but
that doesn't mean they're benign.
The FDA has released
a series of advisories
about the risks that
include patient deaths.
Wait. How could someone
suffer a stomach perforation
with a smooth rounded object? By
causing the patient to puke so much
they rupture their stomach
and die, that's how.
Nausea and vomiting are unsurprisingly
very common side effects,
affecting the majority of those who
have balloons placed inside them.
Persistent vomiting likely
also explains cases of
life-threatening nutrient deficiencies
after balloon implantation.
Some complications,
such as bowel obstruction,
are due to the balloon deflating, but
others, oddly enough, are due to
the balloons suddenly overinflating,
causing pain, vomiting, abdominal
distention. This was first noticed
in breast implants, as
documented in reports such as
"The Phenomenon of the Spontaneously
Autoinflating Breast Implant."
Out of nowhere, the
implants just start growing,
increasing breast volume by
an average of more than 50%.
"It remains," one review noted,
"an underreported and poorly
understood phenomenon."
Interestingly, breast implants
were actually used as some
of the first failed experimental
intragastric balloons.
As with any medical decision, though,
it's all about risks versus benefits.
Industry-funded trials display notable
weight loss, but it's hard to tease out
the effect of the balloon alone from
the accompanying supervised diet
and lifestyle changes prescribed
along with them in the studies.
In drug trials, you can randomize
subjects to sugar pills,
but how do you eliminate the placebo
effect of undergoing a procedure?
Perform sham surgery.
In 2002, a courageous study was published
in the New England Journal of Medicine.
The most common orthopedic surgery,
arthroscopic surgery of the knee, was
put to the test. Billions of dollars are
spent sticking scopes into knee joints
and cutting away damaged tissue
in osteoarthritis and knee injuries,
but does it actually work?
Knee pain sufferers were randomized
to get the actual surgery versus
a sham surgery in which they
actually sliced into people's knees
and pretended to perform the procedure,
complete with splashing saline,
but never actually did
anything within the joint.
The trial caused an uproar.
How could you randomize people
to get cut open for fake surgery?
Professional medical associations
questioned the ethics of the surgeons
as well as the sanity of the patients
who agreed to be part of the trial.
But guess what happened?
Sure, the surgical patients got better,
but so did the placebo patients.
The surgeries had no actual effect.
Currently, rotator cuff shoulder surgery
is facing the same crisis of confidence.
When intragastric balloons were put
to the test, sham-controlled trials show
both older and newer devices sometimes
fail to offer any weight loss benefit.
Even when they do work, the weight loss
may be temporary because balloons
are only allowed to stay in
for 6 months, at which point
the deflation risk gets too great.
Why can't you just keep
putting new ones in?
That's been tried and failed to
improve long-term weight outcomes.
A sham-controlled trial showed
that any effects of the balloon
on appetite and satiety
may vanish with time,
perhaps as your body gets
used to the new normal.
What sham surgery trials
have shown us is that some of
our most popular surgeries
are themselves shams.
Doctors like to pride themselves on
being men and women of science.
We rightly rail, for example, against
the antivaccination movement.
Many of us in medicine have been
troubled by the political trend
of people choosing their own facts.
But when I read that some of these still-
popular surgeries are not only useless
but may actually make things worse
— for example, increasing the risk
of progression to a total
knee replacement —
I can't help but think
we are hardly immune
to our own versions of fake
news and alternative facts.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts Podcast
landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
My latest two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”,
available on e-book, audiobook,
or actual book.
And the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”,
with more than 100 recipes for
delicious and nutritious meals.
All the proceeds I receive from
the sales of my books go to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads, no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.